If I recall correctly,
Jeśli dobrze pamiętam,
your host is physically in its late teens, yes?
twój gospodarz to nastolatek.
Yeah, that sounds about right.
Zgadza się.
Then I believe I'll ask you to do this.
Więc mam do ciebie prośbę.
I'd like you to keep a close eye on the boy
Obserwuj tego chłopaka, ale go nie zabijaj.
-Is there any point to that? -Yes.
- Ma to sens? - Ma.
He poses some danger to us,
Jest dla nas zagrożeniem,
but he is also a valuable asset in determining
ale też potrzebujemy go, żeby określić przyszłość naszego gatunku.
Izumi Shinichi, huh.
Izumi Shinichi, tak?
AUTHOR: HITOSHI IWAAKI
AUTOR: HITOSHI IWAAKI
FREEZING POINT
PUNKT ZAMARZANIA
Yo.
Hejka.
Kana.
Kana.
You going to see him again?
Znowu się z nim spotkasz?
"Him"?
Z kim?
The guy trying to pretend he's a hero.
Z tym, który zgrywa bohatera.
Let me through. I'm going home.
Zejdź mi z drogi. Idę do domu.
What's with you, Kana?
Co z tobą?
You're hurting me. Let go.
To boli. Puszczaj.
Don't tell me you're actually into him.
Nie mów, że się w nim podkochujesz.
That's none of your business.
To nie twoja sprawa.
Kamijo, look.
Kamijo, patrz.
Mitsuo?
Mitsuo?
Hey, you bum.
Cześć, menelu.
Are you back to nab another girl?
Będziesz dręczył kolejną dziewczynę?
-Is he here? -"He"?
- Jest tu? - Kto?
That poser called Izumi or whatever.
Ten pozer Izumi.
What gives you the right to…
Jak śmiesz…
Hey, Izumi!
Izumi! Mitsuo chce z tobą pogadać.
Oh, you again.
Znowu ty.
Who the hell are you?
Kim ty jesteś, do cholery?
Here again?
Znowu tutaj?
Can you keep it brief?
Możesz się streszczać?
I have to meet up with someone.
Umówiłem się z kimś.
Did you bang Kana?
Spałeś z Kaną?
Don't play dumb, you bastard!
Nie udawaj głupka, draniu!
You've got it all wrong.
Coś ci się pomyliło.
I haven't even seen her recently and I was away on a trip before that.
Ostatnio jej nie widziałem. Byłem też na wycieczce.
A trip?
Wycieczce?
Anyway, there's your answer.
Masz odpowiedź.
Screw that!
Walić to!
Don't.
Przestań. Tym razem będzie inaczej.
Why, you!
Ty cholerny…
Hey, are you okay?
Nic ci nie jest?
Izumi-kun!
Izumi-kun!
I heard about what's going on from Kamijo-kun at the school gate.
Kamijo-kun powiedział mi, co się dzieje.
It's fine. Nothing's going on.
Nic się nie dzieje.
I'll leave your shoe here.
Położę go tutaj.
Hey, want to stop in here?
Wejdziemy tutaj?
I'm starving.
Umieram z głodu.
Izumi-kun, did something happen on your trip?
Coś się wydarzyło podczas wycieczki?
Huh?
To znaczy?
You're so different now.
Zmieniłeś się.
I was just using my dad's injury as an excuse to ditch school for a bit.
Wykorzystałem wypadek taty jako wymówkę, żeby nie chodzić do szkoły.
Izumi-kun.
Izumi-kun.
You are Izumi Shinichi-kun, right?
Jesteś Izumi Shinichi-kun, prawda?
Well, I wonder about that.
Też się zastanawiam.
Oh, come on.
Żartuję.
I'm me, of course.
Jestem sobą.
And you're Murano Satomi-san, right?
Ty jesteś Murano Satomi-san, prawda?
Yup!
Tak!
Oh! I can sense it.
Czuję to!
He's coming closer!
Zbliża się!
Why do I know that?
Skąd to wiem?
Soon, he'll come up those stairs.
Zaraz wejdzie po schodach.
See, I knew it!
Wiedziałam!
I'm home.
Wróciłem.
Dad.
Tato.
Oh, Shinichi.
Shinichi.
Hungry?
Jesteś głodny?
I ate something.
Jadłem.
What about you?
A ty?
I'm not hungry.
Nie jestem.
Try to go easy on the drinking.
Nie pij tyle.
You should eat something, too.
I zjedz coś.
Yeah.
Dobrze.
I looked it up online
W Internecie polecają,
and they recommend hiring a housekeeper in this kind of situation.
żeby w takiej sytuacji zatrudnić gosposię.
-In what kind of situation? -Well, like…
- W jakiej sytuacji? - No…
When your mom…
Gdy mama…
When someone who used to handle your meals suddenly isn't around anymore.
Gdy ktoś, kto gotował, nagle znika.
How can you even think of…
Jak możesz myśleć o…
Never mind.
Nieważne.
If you think hiring a housekeeper is a good idea, go ahead.
Jeśli uważasz, że to dobry pomysł, to zatrudnij gosposię.
I wonder if something's wrong with my heart.
- Wszystko dobrze z moim sercem? - To znaczy?
I can't cry anymore.
Nie potrafię płakać.
Oh, that's all?
I to wszystko?
I feel like I've lost something.
Czuję się, jakbym coś stracił.
Something that's an important part of being human.
Jakąś ważną ludzką cechę.
That's senseless.
To bez sensu.
Since Migi's cells scattered throughout my body,
Odkąd Migi rozprzestrzenił się po moim ciele,
my senses have become very acute.
mam bardzo wyostrzone zmysły.
My hearing is one example.
Na przykład słuch.
If I focus…
Jeśli się skupię…
Oh my! Hashimoto-san's son?
Rety! Syn Hashimoto-sana?
-Yes! Isn't that shocking? -Moving on to traffic information.
- Tak! Szok, nie? - Informacje o korkach.
Metro Expressway Four
Linia czwarta stoi w korku z powodu wypadku…
-Pigs, pigs, pigs, pigs, pigs! -accident, accident, accident, accident,
- Świnie! - Wypadku…
What's wrong?
Co się stało?
Oh, nothing!
Nic!
I just heard something.
Coś słyszałem.
Izumi-kun?
Izumi-kun?
Sorry. Can you go on ahead without me?
Przepraszam. Idź beze mnie.
It's calling…
Woła o pomoc.
Can we save him?
Uratujemy go?
Its internal organs are mush. They're irreparable.
Wewnętrzne organy są zniszczone.
It'll die within ten minutes.
Umrze za dziesięć minut.
Sorry.
Przepraszam.
We can't help you.
Nie możemy ci pomóc.
But this is better than dying in a noisy place like that, right?
Ale lepiej umrzeć tak niż w głośnym miejscu, prawda?
Izumi-kun.
Izumi-kun.
This guy's about to die.
On zaraz umrze.
-I was kind of scared. -Huh?
- Przestraszyłam się. - Co?
I thought that you'd changed.
Myślałam, że się zmieniłeś.
I mean, you used to be a bit more nervous before.
Wcześniej byłeś bardziej nerwowy.
But that's what I found kind of cute about you.
Ale to mi się w tobie podobało.
It made me feel safe.
Czułam się bezpiecznie.
But since the trip,
Ale odkąd wróciłeś z wycieczki,
I thought you had become kind of cold.
wydawałeś mi się oziębły.
I guess I was just imagining it, though.
Chyba tylko mi się wydawało.
You're being so kind now.
Teraz jesteś taki dobry.
It's dead.
Nie żyje.
What?
Co?
Its heart stopped beating.
Jego serce przestało bić.
Let's go.
Chodźmy.
We're already late, though.
Jesteśmy spóźnieni.
&lrm;PUSH
POPCHNIJ
Izumi-kun?
Izumi-kun?
Huh?
Co?
How could you? I can't believe you did that!
Jak mogłeś to zrobić! Nie wierzę!
You threw the puppy in the garbage!
Wyrzuciłeś go do śmieci!
Oh, do you think the janitor will be mad?
Dozorca będzie zły?
That's not what I'm talking about!
Nie o to mi chodzi!
The puppy!
Szczeniak!
The poor puppy!
Biedny szczeniak!
Poor? But it's dead.
Biedny? Ale on nie żyje.
But… But that's not…
Ale nie o to…
It's dead.
Nie żyje.
A dead dog isn't a dog anymore.
Martwy pies to nie pies.
It's a dog-shaped lump of meat.
To kawałek mięsa.
You're different.
Zmieniłeś się.
Murano.
Murano.
You are different!
Jesteś inny!
The Izumi-kun I knew wouldn't…
Izumi-kun, którego znałam…
He wouldn't…
On by tego…
Murano?
Murano!
"Different"?
„Inny”?
Have I changed?
Zmieniłem się?
Migi!
Migi!
What?
Co?
You've been listening, right?
Słuchałeś?
I apparently said something strange to her.
Chyba powiedziałem coś dziwnego.
What did I say wrong?
Co powiedziałem nie tak?
You said nothing wrong.
Nic.
Not from my perspective, anyway.
Z mojego punktu widzenia.
But you are quite different from the way you used to be.
Ale jesteś inny niż kiedyś.
"A dog-shaped lump of meat".
„To kawałek mięsa”.
That's something I'd be more likely to say.
Ja mówię takie rzeczy.
I see.
Rozumiem.
Thanks, Migi.
Dzięki, Migi.
The dog's body will break down and become nutrients
Ciało psa ulegnie rozkładowi i odżywi to drzewo.
If I'd done this in the first place,
Gdybym od razu to zrobił,
Murano wouldn't hate me now.
Murano nadal by mnie lubiła.
Murano.
Murano.
I guess I won't get anywhere today.
Dziś nic nie wskóram.
I should give her space and talk to her later.
Dam jej spokój i później z nią porozmawiam.
Shinichi.
Shinichi.
Huh?
- Tak? - Jest tu jeden z moich.
What?
Co?
Don't tell me, Tamiya Ryoko's back?
Tamiya Ryoko wróciła?
No, this one seems like a different individual.
Nie, to ktoś inny.
It can't be Uda-san and Parasite, right?
To nie Uda-san i Parasite, prawda?
Is it here to kill me?
Chce mnie zabić?
-I don't sense any hostility. -What should we do?
- Nie czuję wrogości. - Co robimy?
For now, let's meet it in a public place.
Spotkajmy się z nim w miejscu publicznym.
Meet an enemy?
Spotkanie z wrogiem?
It may not be our enemy.
Może nie być naszym wrogiem.
Despite reacting to our presence,
Zareagował na naszą obecność,
it's continuing to calmly approach us.
ale zbliża się do nas ze spokojem.
I believe this one may be the Tamiya Ryoko type,
Może być podobny do Tamiyi Ryoko.
as in, the type you can reason with.
Można go przekonać.
Reason with? What do you even mean by that?
- Przekonać? O czym ty mówisz? - Idzie.
Hey. Izumi-kun, right?
Cześć. Izumi-kun, tak?
Who are you?
Kim jesteś?
You're different from how I imagined you'd be.
Jesteś inny, niż sobie wyobrażałem.
You seem quite strong.
Wyglądasz na silnego.
Why are you at school?
Co robisz w szkole?
What are you here for?
Po co tu przyszedłeś?
Hey, Izumi. What are you arguing about?
Izumi. O co się kłócicie?
I haven't seen you around. Are you a transfer student?
Nie kojarzę cię. Jesteś z wymiany?
You're interfering.
Przeszkadzasz.
I'm Shimada Hideo.
Jestem Shimada Hideo.
I recently settled on that as my name.
Tak się ostatnio nazwałem.
I thought I should start off
Pomyślałem, że się z tobą zaprzyjaźnię.
What the hell is up with this guy?
Co to za koleś?
Oh, I must go.
Muszę już iść.
Izumi-kun, can you show me to Class 3?
Izumi-kun, gdzie jest klasa trzecia?
Class 3?
Klasa trzecia?
That's Murano's class.
To klasa Murano.
I'm looking forward to gym.
Nie mogę się doczekać wuefu.
I think it's a joint session between our classes.
Mamy go razem, prawda?
If I went all-out, I'd set a world record.
Jeśli dam z siebie wszystko, pobiję rekord świata.
Ten point eight seconds?
Co? 10,8 sekundy?
It's unusual to transfer schools at this time of year.
Dziwnie tak zmieniać szkołę o tej porze roku.
Yeah, he said he had to move because of his dad's job.
Musiał się przeprowadzić przez pracę taty.
I'm jealous.
Zazdroszczę.
I wish I was in the same class as Hide.
Chciałabym chodzić do klasy z Hide’em.
"Hide"?
„Hide’em”?
Hide for Shimada Hideo.
Shimada Hideo, czyli Hide.
I thought you liked Izumi-kun.
Myślałam, że lubisz Izumi-kuna.
What? Like you don't.
Co? A ty nie?
Huh? Quit teasing me.
Co? Nie drocz się ze mną.
But Izumi-kun's with Satomi, right?
Izumi-kun jest z Satomi, prawda?
Huh?
Co?
Well, um…
No…
Sports are very good.
Sport jest dobry.
The more you play, the better you become at using your body.
Im więcej grasz, tym lepiej panujesz nad ciałem.
Why drag this out?
Po co to przeciągać?
Are you planning to kill me once I let my guard down?
Zabijesz mnie, gdy stracę czujność?
You misunderstand me.
Źle mnie zrozumiałeś.
Is that what your right hand thinks as well?
Twoja prawa ręka też tak myśli?
Didn't Tamiya Ryoko send you to get rid of me?
Tamiya Ryoko przysłała cię, żebyś mnie zabił?
Tamiya Ryoko?
Tamiya Ryoko?
Oh, she has a different name now.
Teraz inaczej się nazywa.
But yes, she's the one who told me about you.
Tak, ona mi o tobie powiedziała.
That's not what this is about, though.
Ale nie o to chodzi.
I have no intention
Nie mam zamiaru
of harming you or anyone around you at this school for that matter.
krzywdzić ciebie ani osób z tej szkoły.
Actually, I haven't harmed any humans in recent memory.
Właściwie to nie skrzywdziłem żadnego człowieka.
I subsist on a diet similar to that of humans.
Moja dieta podobna jest do ludzkiej.
If parasites learned to exist without killing humans,
Gdyby pasożyty umiały żyć bez zabijania ludzi,
there'd be no problem, right?
nie byłoby problemu, prawda?
You expect me to believe you?
Mam ci uwierzyć?
We're starting to look for a way
Szukamy sposobu,
We wanted the two of you to think about that,
Chcemy, żebyście o tym pomyśleli.
given that you're somewhere between humanity and our kind.
Łączycie oba gatunki.
Interesting.
Ciekawe.
The things you say always manage to pique my interest.
Mówisz bardzo interesujące rzeczy.
Don't they?
Prawda?
However, I am only inclined to believe half of what you're saying.
Ale wierzę tylko w połowę z nich.
Oh, okay.
Dobrze.
Well, I don't desire conflict, either.
Nie chcę konfliktu.
Let's call it a day.
Skończmy na dzisiaj.
Let's go, Shinichi.
Chodźmy, Shinichi.
Huh? Why now?
Co? Dlaczego teraz?
What's going on?
Co się dzieje?
We weren't even done talking.
Nie dokończyliśmy rozmowy.
Shinichi, I'm going to sleep.
Shinichi, idę spać.
-You're drowsy again? -I'll be out for about four hours.
- Znów jesteś śpiący? - Wstanę za cztery godziny.
If he learns of this weakness, who knows what he will do?
Kto wie, co zrobi, jeśli dowie się o tej słabości?
Izumi-kun.
Izumi-kun.
I was really shocked when you did that,
Byłam w szoku, że to zrobiłeś,
but most people wouldn't have given that puppy any thought at all.
ale większość osób nie zwróciłaby uwagi na tego szczeniaka.
That's right.
To prawda.
I shouldn't have said that he's cold and unfeeling now.
Nie powinnam mówić, że jest oziębły i nie ma uczuć.
What should I do?
Co mam zrobić?
If he's really thinking about coexistence with humans,
Jeśli naprawdę chce koegzystować z ludźmi,
maybe we can figure out a clever workaround.
może znajdziemy jakieś mądre rozwiązanie.
No. How I can trust them?
Nie. Mogę im ufać?
They're merciless!
Są bezlitosne!
They may be highly intelligent,
Są inteligentne, ale pod względem emocji to robaki.
That's right.
To prawda.
How could I forget?
Jak mogłem zapomnieć?
Forget.
Zapomnij.
I'll expose them someday!
Kiedyś je zdemaskuję!
Hi.
Cześć.
About the other day, um…
Co do tamtego zajścia…
It's okay.
Nic się nie stało.
Talk to you later.
Pogadamy innym razem.
You jerk.
Kretynie.
Why did you have to scare Murano?
Dlaczego wystraszyłeś Murano?
I have a superpower
Mam nadprzyrodzoną moc.
and it lets me sense my soul mate.
Mogę wyczuć swoją bratnią duszę.
Here he comes.
Idzie.
Hello.
Cześć.
-What can I do for you? -Sorry, wrong person.
- O co chodzi? - Przepraszam. Pomyliłam się.
That's strange.
To dziwne. Myślałam, że to Izumi.
Izumi?
Izumi?
What do you mean by that?
To znaczy?
Huh?
Co?
When you mistake someone for another person,
Gdy kogoś z kimś pomylisz,
it's because they look similar in appearance, right?
to przez to, że jest podobny do tamtej osoby?
How are Izumi and I similar?
Jestem podobny do Izumiego?
Hey, I said "sorry".
Przeprosiłam.
Hey! What are you doing?
Hej! Co robisz?
That sounds like…
To brzmi jak…
Let me go!
Puść mnie!
I just want to talk to you for a bit.
Chcę z tobą porozmawiać.
You! What do you think you're doing?
Hej! Co ty wyprawiasz?
Help!
Pomocy!
I just wanted to talk to her.
Chciałem z nią porozmawiać.
She seems to be rather perceptive.
Jest bardzo spostrzegawcza.
If anything happens to anyone I know, I'll kill you first.
Jeśli coś się stanie moim znajomym, to od razu cię zabiję.
You think I'm not capable of doing that?
Myślisz, że nie dam rady?
You're a scary one.
Można się ciebie bać.
Like I said many times, I have no intention of fighting you.
Jak już mówiłem, nie chcę z tobą walczyć.
What's with him?
Co to za jeden?
His eyes don't look right.
Ma dziwne oczy.
His right hand seemed to have a really weak signal.
Jego prawa ręka wydaje bardzo słaby sygnał.
Was I imagining it?
Czy mi się wydaje?
Izumi, are you sure you aren't actually strong?
Jesteś pewny, że nie jesteś silny?
Huh?
Co?
Hey, Izumi, can you walk me to the train station?
Izumi, odprowadzisz mnie na dworzec?
I'm scared that guy might be there.
Boję się, że on tam będzie.
Oh, sure.
Jasne.
Not again. God, this sucks!
Tylko nie to. Boże, nie!
What's wrong?
Co się stało?
Telepathy?
Telepatia?
Yeah.
Tak.
I can somehow tell when you're close.
Czuję, gdy jesteś blisko.
I don't know why I got it wrong just now, though.
Ale nie wiem, dlaczego teraz się pomyliłam.
Well, it's not like I was totally off since you came along right away, I guess.
W sumie za chwilę przyszedłeś.
I don't think that's really a good thing.
To raczej nic dobrego.
Huh?
Co?
I mean, whatever you're sensing
To, co czujesz,
might be weird wavelengths given off by dangerous guys like him.
to mogą być sygnały wysyłane przez takich niebezpiecznych gości jak on.
So you're a dangerous guy, too?
Ty też jesteś niebezpieczny?
Sure, I am, too.
Jasne, że tak.
So don't go near guys like him anymore.
Więc nie zbliżaj się do takich jak on.
I guess I'll use this face as bait today.
Użyję tej twarzy jako przynęty.
That female has had a healthy lifestyle.
Ta kobieta prowadzi zdrowy tryb życia.
Her skin has a nice sheen to it, too.
Ma błyszczącą cerę.
Hey, are you lost?
Zgubiłaś się?
Um, I…
Ja…
I can help you if you'd like.
Pomogę ci, jeśli chcesz.
Dad.
Tato.
I know.
Wiem.
I'm going to bed.
Idę spać.
Goodnight.
Dobranoc.
Shinichi.
Shinichi.
When did you become so strong?
Kiedy stałeś się taki silny?
Are you…
Czy jesteś…
made of steel?
ze stali?
Sorry.
Przepraszam.
There.
Gotowe.
I think it came out pretty good.
Dobrze wyszło.
Next time, "Beyond Good and Evil."
Następny odcinek: „Ponad dobrem i złem”.